Slave to love, nursing those from others born,
Na escravidão do amor a criar filhos alheios
And like the kind, self-vulning pelican,
rasgou qual pelicano as maternais entranhas
Selflessly, to her Land her breast she tore.
e deu à pátria livre em holocausto os seios.
Verses by Ciro Costa.
Versos de Ciro Costa.
It was mainly due to the outlets left by the Catholic Church
Foi através das irmandades,
and through the brotherhoods
principalmente das brechas que a igreja católica tinha
that the black population could have a minimal bond to society.
que a população preta conseguia ter algum laço de sociabilidade.
Important bonds, though, right?
Importantes, inclusive, né?
That's why the black brotherhoods
Por isso que as irmandades sempre tem um mistério
have always had mysteries.
que sempre envolve as irmandades, né?
We know that there's always some African-originated practice in
Você vê que sempre tem alguma prática de origem africana numa irmandade preta
a black brotherhood. It's never a catholic only brotherhood.
Ela nunca é uma irmandade totalmente católica.
It always has something referring to religions of African descent.
Ela tem sempre um pouquinho das religiões de matriz africana.
And the religions of African descent have always respected the practices
Inclusive as religiões de matriz africana sempre respeitaram as práticas das irmandades.
in the brotherhood. Those bonds were not only made in Sao Paulo.
Tem ligações históricas não só em São Paulo, por exemplo
For example, in the state of Bahia, the Da Boa Morte Brotherhood was
no recôncavo baiano a irmandade da boa morte
bonded to Afro-Brazilian temples of mainly Gege origins.
e os terreiros de origem Gêge principalmente.
It's not different in Sao Paulo. Many Afro-Brazilian temples
Em São Paulo não deixa de ser diferente, né?
of Sao Paulo offer masses of Thanksgiving here.
Muito terreiro em São Paulo vem fazer Missa de Ação de graças aqui
Specially here, by the Mãe Preta statue...
Inclusive na Mãe Preta aqui...
which is a pretty questionable symbol, isn't it?
que também é um símbolo bem contestável, né?
It's related to the idea of the motherly black woman,
Que ainda está ligado à idéia de mulher preta materna, né?
still seen as a wet nurse.
E ainda Ama de Leite, né?
Although these really are the kind of references we have of them...
Mas são referências, né?
Isn't it a little contradictory?
... é meio contraditório, né?...